Good morning, world. I've been living in
Anakia, an abandoned Japanese home for
over a year now. It's the middle of
winter and it's freezing cold inside.
I know, I know. This uh fluffy robe is
kind of sexy, isn't it? But don't let it
distract you because I'm going to need
to wear it for my morning routine. Come
join me. So, the first thing I like to
do when I crawl out of bed [music] is to
heat up the living room/off.
And it's uh
zero. [music] It was minus one before,
but it's warmed up, so it's it's cold
inside. And I got to heat [music] it up
fast. So, I use my kerosene gas fan
heater.
It takes a while to start, but it's
pretty fast and hot.
I also have my mini split air comb that
I need to turn on and get started
because it takes about 5 to 10 minutes.
But when you're trying to heat the room
from 0 to 20, uh, you need all the help
you can get. That's why two units. Plus,
I also plan to use it after I turn the
kerosene heater off.
By the way, air cone stands for air
conditioner, but it does heating as
well. It's a heat pump system. And in
winter, this outdoor unit, despite it
being freezing, it can capture some of
the thermal energy in the air. And using
the magic of technology, create warm air
inside. It's a lot more efficient than
straight up electrical heaters, but it
does take time to heat up.
While the living room is heating up, I'm
going to get the coffee going. Now, I
would use my electric kettle, but that
would risk the electricity getting shut
off. Why is that, you ask? Well, this
thing is my electrical panel. I don't
even know how old it is, but it's old.
We upgraded it to 30 amps, but even
then, if you try to run the air con and
the electric kettle at the same time, it
will trip the circuit breaker. And if
I'm not careful about managing my
electrical devices, well, let me show
you. This thermal fuse will literally
melt and then I'll have to very
carefully replace it.
It's no simple flip of a switch. So,
that's why I use my propane gas stove to
heat up the water and avoid any
electrical issues.
Looks like it's boiling.
Let's check the [music] temperature.
Too hot. Too hot.
Because my cups are freezing. I'm going
to run them over with hot water. Oo,
nice and hot. Then I put the milk in.
Sorry, I like milk with my coffee.
Uh-oh.
And then I'm going to heat up the milk
in the microwave. The microwave only
draws 600 [music] W, which is only 6
amps in this 100vt system. And this
won't shut down all the electricity. How
do I know that? Trial and error, my
friend. Trial and error.
All right. Steaming hot milk.
There we go. Well, the morning cafe olay
kind ofish because this [music] is not
espresso.
I just got this foot heater a few weeks
ago and I'm really loving it. I'm one of
those people that constantly have cold
hands and feet.
I was resorting to filling up buckets of
hot water to soak my toes in before I
found this bad boy on Amazon. It only
uses 200 watts of energy at max output,
but provides 5D heating. I know, I know.
5D sounds like such dumb marketing mumbo
jumbo, but it is handy that there are
heating elements on each side, which
there are five of, one, two, three,
four, five. Hence the 5D heating. I
prefer the floor portion of the heater
to give a little more heat, but
otherwise very worth it for me and it
doesn't trip the circuit breaker. While
I do admittedly have cold feet, it's
also true that there's a big temperature
difference between my head and my feet.
For example, it's 10° C at my feet, but
over here at my head, this is basically
19° C. That's a 9° C difference. After
the room heats up, I turn off the
kerosene fan heater.
You're not supposed to use it without
ventilating the room. Bad emissions can
build up like carbon monoxide. Carbon
monoxide. [laughter] Which is why I have
this carbon monoxide detector.
Luckily, the sun comes out from behind
the mountain around 10:00 a.m. to help
add heat to the place. If I had proper
insulation in place, I would be able to
turn off the aircon unit because over
here there's southacing windows and the
sun provides a lot of heat. Speaking of
insulation, you may have heard that
Japanese homes have no insulation.
That's not true. My house built 10 years
ago has insulation in between the walls.
And my new mini hotel, Silver Daisy Stay
Niko, where I'm standing at right now,
also has it. But it is true that old
Japanese homes often don't have
insulation. The reasoning I hear is that
the homes are designed for summer and
specifically to combat humidity, which
results in mold. You want to keep air
flow. You don't want to seal things up.
If you look below on merely old houses,
they have vents built into the
foundation to let air pass through. But
if you go really old, you won't even
find a foundation. The frame is put up
on stones and the air easily passes
underneath through the house and up
through the floorboards. In the summer,
plants were growing up through a section
of the aka's floorboards. Most of you
will know that Japan has sliding doors
that are made of paper called shoi. But
did you know that down below underneath
the tatami mats, paper is also a
strategy to provide insulation,
newspaper to be exact. I found this out
because when we went to replace the
tatamis, we were able to read the news
from years past. So in an effort to make
the room we plan to sleep in a little
more insulated, we did a bit of
renovations. Instead of the original
tatami, we decided to put in laminate
flooring. But first, below it, we put
down blue styrofoam. For the walls, we
replaced sections of the Fusimma, the
sliding doors, with some of the blue
styrofoam sandwiched between plywood.
And while I think this has helped, it
still gets really cold. Given enough
time, the air will slowly leak out and
the temperature inside will be nearly
the same as the temperature outside. But
our biggest issue was the living room.
This place was drafty. In our first
year, we thought our weak point were
these shoji screen doors, as after all,
they are made of paper.
So, we put this blue styrofoam behind it
and covered it in some silver insulation
from the hundred yen shop, Daiso. Then,
we put that same insulation over the
floorboards and child safety foam mats
on top of that. Plus, we also added blue
styrofoam to the sections of the wall
that were thin plywood panels. This, I
felt, basically did nothing. It was
still as cold and drafty as could be.
Two major reasons in my mind were that
the windows were not only single pane,
but they had gaps between the panes and
the frame. Cold air was leaking through
like a civ, and the ceiling with gaps
big enough that I can imagine animals
scurrying through was probably not doing
a great job of keeping the warm air in.
So, I decided to greenhouse the place. I
got the vinyl you use for green houses
and tried to seal off the patio doors.
Then from inside the house, I tried to
seal the ceiling. And you know what?
This actually worked a ton to help keep
the warm air in longer and make the
place a lot less drafty. But it's not
perfect. As mentioned previously, the
floor level is a lot cooler than the
head level. But hey, you got to take the
W's where you can. Now, like I said
before, I read that Japanese homes are
designed for the summer, but why ignore
the winter? Well, I also read that in
the winter, the design is to heat the
individual, not the room or not the
house. That's why items like this, the
kotatu, are very popular in the winter.
For your sake, I've made bear the
kotatu. It's basically a table with a
heater stuck underneath it with a
blanket that wraps around it. So, you
got hot toes and a cool head. We never
use it because the room is in the north
and it's the coldest room in the house.
Now, I know that you don't come to the
channel for fashion advice, or at least
I hope you haven't been, but I thought
it imperative to address clothing
choices. As mentioned before, the goal
is to heat up the person, not the space.
So, clothing that'll keep you warm is a
must. I love my big fluffy marino wool
socks. Funny thing is, I've had these
for years and never wore them because I
thought they were too thick and hot. But
here in this old drafty house, they're
perfect.
Some people say you should go with heat
tech from Uniqlo, an affordable, easy
choice for your under layers. I
personally find that when I get too hot
in them, I can't easily take them off.
That's why I've gone this fluffy robe
strategy. This one I got from Ntori, the
Japanese IKEA. I can easily take it on
and off and it covers me from head to
toe or nearly to my toes. which is why
in addition to my marino wool socks, I
have these fluffy slippers.
For the outside, one thing I got from
Unilo is this thick puffer jacket. I
lived a lot of time on the west coast of
Canada, and there's an everpresent
danger of rain throughout the winter, so
I've always taken to layering and
wearing a Gortex shell, but that
requires two layers of clothing, whereas
this big puffy jacket is only one, and
it's a very warm one. This is my
favorite clothing purchase of 2025. And
this brings us to today's video sponsor,
Uniqlo. Nah, I joke, but if there was a
sponsor, I'd make it my mini hotel,
Silver Daisy Stay Nico. Since this is a
new build, it actually does have
insulation. Insulation in the floors,
insulation in the walls, insulation in
the ceilings, and double pane windows.
How glorious. It also has modern
circuits that can handle the power draw
of air cone units and ceramic fan
heaters simultaneously.
This ceramic fan heater is definitely
something I can't use in the old house
as its 12 amp draw will definitely break
the circuit in no time. In any case, if
you stay at Silver Daisy Stay Nico, rest
assured that you'll get your heat and
hot water in a wellinssulated building.
And if you're really cold, you can hop
into our Hinoi sauna. And if you get too
hot, jump in the cold bath. It's
obviously not full of water right now,
but believe it or not, guests do use it
in this cold weather. So, you might be
wondering, why not leave these kerosene
gas fan heaters that I use in the AKA
with guests? Well, for one, you need to
fill them up. The most common and
cost-effective way to do it is to go to
a gas station and fill up jerry cans. or
you can get companies to come directly
to your house and do this, which is what
happens with our propane gas. But to get
the gas into the heater, you have to
remove the heater's tank. Then you take
it to your jerry can and use this handy
battery operated pump to transfer the
kerosene.
Now you wait as it transfers.
When you take out the pump, you make
sure to pour out a little bit for the
homies.
Then you close it up and put the tank
back in the heater.
While refilling is a pain in the butt,
my real worry is the exhaust that comes
from burning the kerosene gas in this
device. Now, in this old AKA, I don't
think the exhaust is too much of a
problem, but in the well-insulated
Silver Daisy Stay Nico, it um I think
that is a real big issue where if you
don't ventilate properly, it could be
quite dangerous for guests.
[sighs and gasps]
I've cleaned up and now it's time for
dinner. And I'll share with you a saying
that I just made up. If my olive oil
don't pour, it's too damn cold.
Technically, too cold is 3° C. So, I've
resorted to
heating up my olive oil with hot water,
just like I do with the handle of my
knife.
We don't ever heat up the kitchen as it
seems easier to dress warmer for the
little bit of time we want to use it to
make food or drinks. I mean, we'd spend
more time heating it up than we'd
actually spend using it. Plus, if we
ever want to cook food, we have the
heated living room.
That's because we can use this kerosene
heater. It's like its cousin, the
kerosene fan heater, but no fan. Well,
that's not totally true. There are a
couple other differences. One, since
there's no fan, it can be battery
operated and thus be easily movable as
well as a great backup in case of a
power outage. Second, it has a stove
top. It can be used to make Japanese
classics like Tongjiu or Yakiimo.
Since it's dry in the winter, people
often heat water on the stove, making it
do triple duty as a space heater, water
boiler, and humidifier. Despite this
protective cage, this is the most
dangerous of them all. You don't want to
touch this by accident.
Seeing water. This reminds me. I forgot
to talk about the toilet.
If you've seen some of my previous
videos, you'd understand what I'm
talking about. Old Japanese homes may
seem primitive, but they do have one
technological advantage. The heated
toilet seat and the bedet that sprays
hot water. Standard for decades now is a
socket in the toilet room specifically
meant to power the washlet. These
washlets are so common in Japan. I'd be
shocked if any new home built in the
past decade didn't have one. I don't
know the exact reason why washlets were
initially developed, but now that you
know that many rooms in a Japanese home
are unheated, you can probably
understand why washlets are so
ubiquitous. Yet another unheated room is
the bathing room. Initially, I thought
I'd have to find a way to heat this up,
but with the hot water being heated up
to 47 degrees, I find the room gets hot
and steamy in no time. So, I haven't had
an issue with showering, as it was only
chilly until I stepped into the stream
of water. This stone floor would take a
lot longer to heat up, which is why this
white foam mat comes in super handy. And
if you ever get tired, oh, you can just
lie down and relax.
Many people would also fill up the bath
as modern baths in Japan can be filled
and refilled at the push of a button.
>> But ours is old, dirty, and needs to be
filled up manually. The horror. That's
why we end up going to the onsen, the
hotring. I don't know how much winters
contribute to Japan's love of onens, but
I think there's certainly nothing better
than sitting in one on a cold, snowy
winter night. A nice warm bath gets your
blood circulating, and it's a great way
to both relax and heat up before going
to sleep.
Speaking of sleep, let's move on to my
nighttime routine.
This looks wasteful, doesn't it?
Well, it's the price to pay if you don't
want your pipes to freeze and burst in
the winter. Now, my plumber specifically
told me to drip the hot water, which
didn't make any sense to me. Why would I
waste the hot water? And wouldn't the
cold water freeze first? The explanation
I was told was that by flowing the hot
water at a low rate, the heater doesn't
actually turn on. So, you're not wasting
energy heating water that's going down
the drain. And by running the hot water,
it pulls cold water through the ondemand
propane gas heater, which means it keeps
both the cold and hot water moving,
helping to prevent freezing. So, you're
supposed to let the water flow, but how
much?
The end goal is to keep the water
flowing, not freezing. And in harsher
temperatures with less insulation, a
steadier flow is safer. Now ask me how I
know this. How do I know?
So, so good.
I'd like to say this only happened once,
but I think it happened two or three
times. We ended up putting heat tape
around the hot water pipes on the
outside, as well as insulation. for our
hotel. We put heat tape and insulation
around our garden hose that runs to the
sauna area. And so far, it's been
working great. All right, it's like
minus 3 outside and
this is frozen water off it. So, I don't
know if this is actually working or not,
but let's see.
Oh, no,
it's coming out in little spurts. Oh, it
works.
Oh, that's cool.
But this begs a question. Why in modern
Japan are frozen pipes a problem? In
Canada, I've never heard of this issue
in any homes I've lived in. I know about
shutting off the outside water or
turning off water in cabins when you're
not there. It turns out that in most
homes in Canada, we pipe water in below
the frost line into a basement that
doesn't freeze. And the basement doesn't
freeze because you have central heating.
heating that you leave on, whether you
leave for an hour, a day, or a week. Why
aren't modern Japanese homes built and
heated this way? I started going down
that rabbit hole, but abandoned it when
I was about to call up the architect who
designed my hotel. Maybe one day I'll
explore that in a different video. But
right now, I'm kind of tired. That's why
I'm going to bed. But first, I have to
turn off the air con unit in the living
room because I want to use the air con
unit in the bedroom. And you know that
if I use both at the same time, that
would result in a cold, dark world.
Here in the bedroom, I recreate my
morning routine where I fire up the
kerosene fan heater
and the air con.
I let it heat up for about 30 minutes
before I get into bed.
In the past, I didn't look forward to
getting in because in between the
sheets, it was ice cold. But while
writing the script for this video, I
found out
or I thought, wouldn't it be better to
have the bed like this because it would
heat up the sheets as well as the inside
of the blankets? And you know what? It
actually does work a lot better. So, I
do this and then I get in and I uh
if I was more ambitious, I'd raise my
bed up on a frame as I know the air on
the ground is a lot cooler than higher
up. For example, it's uh 10.7° C on the
ground. This is despite my air con being
set to 14°.
14 degrees is actually the minimum
temperature the air con unit can heat
to. So that's why I chose that number.
Because of the emissions, you don't want
to run a kerosene heater while you're
sleeping. So I turn it off before going
to bed.
Before we'd sleep with all the heaters
off, and the room would get down to
between 0 and 5° C, which was a bit too
much for me. That's basically sleeping
in a refrigerator. And for those of you
that haven't used an air con in cold
weather, I think it's good to know that
it'll periodically run a defrost cycle
that can run for a few minutes up to 15.
So if your air con unit stops or
suddenly starts blowing cold air, this
is why. Another note, when I was making
this video, I got a CO2 detector. I know
the air quality with kerosene heaters
isn't too great, but I was surprised to
see that it would take 4 hours to get
the CO2 levels down from the not great
for you 3000 range to below 1,000, the
acceptable range. I'm from a city in
Canada called Winnipeg. And us winter
peggers, I think we're proud of the fact
that we can live in a cold climate. And
I also think we like to make fun of
people who complain about the cold who
are from places where it only ever gets
a few degrees below freezing. But after
moving Japan, I now understand that it's
a lot easier to withstand the cold when
you are living in a well-insulated home
that has central heating. The more you
know. Thanks for watching. See you next
time. Peace. What's living in an old
home in the winter like where you're
from?
You know what? I forgot to show you how
we prevent food items from freezing. You
see this white rectangle over here?
Well, we take the item we don't want to
freeze and uh we put it in. It has great
climate control that ensures that
whatever you put in doesn't become a
block of ice in the morning.